<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7410</anchor> <taxon>Reference</taxon> <addr>pl-123</addr><route>pl-123.xml</route>   <authors><author>GRAHAM HUTTON</author> </authors> <title>Programming language semantics: It's easy as 1,2,3</title>   <meta name="doi">10.1017/s0956796823000072</meta></frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Programming language semantics is an important topic in theoretical computer science, but one that beginners often find challenging. This article provides a tutorial introduction to the subject, in which the language of integers and addition is used as a minimal setting in which to present a range of semantic concepts in simple manner
</p></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7411</anchor> <taxon>Computer Science</taxon> <addr>cs-0006</addr><route>cs-0006.xml</route>  <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>  <title>Introduction to Programming Language Semantic</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    I decided to read one paper or article every week.
    This week's topic is programming language semantics, refer to <strong>Graham Huttons</strong>'s 
    paper <link href="pl-123.xml" type="local" addr="pl-123" title="Programming language semantics: It's easy as 1,2,3">Programming language semantics: It's easy as 1,2,3</link>.
</p><p><strong>Semantics</strong> is the general term for the study of meaning.
    <strong>Programming language semantics</strong> gives precise mathematical meaning to programs.
    We use a simple <strong>arithmetic expression language</strong> 
    (including integers and addition only) to illustrate the basic concepts.
    This is an example of <strong>Occam's razor</strong>, a philosophical principle that favours the 
    simplest explanation for a phenomenon.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7412</anchor>    <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>  <title><link href="cs-0006.xml" type="local" addr="cs-0006" title="Introduction to Programming Language Semantic">Introduction to Programming Language Semantic</link> › Arithmetic Expressions</title>  <parent>cs-0006</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
        Now let's define our language of arithmetic expressions
        built up from the set of integers and the operation of addition.
        Use a <strong>context-free</strong> grammar.
        <tex display="block">             E: \equiv \mathbb {Z} | E+E         </tex></p><p>
        An expression is either an integer value or the addition of two sub-expressions.
        We assume that parentheses can be <strong>freely</strong> used as required to disambiguate expressions 
        written in normal textual form. This grammar can be easily translated into 
        a <strong>Haskell</strong> data type.
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">data Expr = Val Integer | Add Expr Expr</code></pre>
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7413</anchor>    <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>  <title><link href="cs-0006.xml" type="local" addr="cs-0006" title="Introduction to Programming Language Semantic">Introduction to Programming Language Semantic</link> › Denotational Semantics</title>  <parent>cs-0006</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
        Now we consider <strong>denotational semantics</strong>, 
        where the terms in a language is defined using a 
        <strong>valuation function</strong> that maps terms into values in an appropriate <strong>semantic domain</strong>.
    </p><p>
        Formally, for a language <tex>T</tex> of syntactic terms comprises
        two components: a set <tex>V</tex> of <strong>semantic values</strong> and a 
        <strong>valuation function</strong> of type <tex>T \to  V</tex> that maps terms to 
        their meanings as values.
        This function is written by enclosing a term in a <strong>semantic brackets</strong> 
        (Also known as Oxford or Strachey brackets),
        writing <tex>\llbracket  t \rrbracket</tex> for the value of term <tex>t</tex>.
        In addition, the valuation function is required to be <strong>compositional</strong>,
        the meaning  of a <strong>compound term</strong> is defined purely in terms of the meaning
        of its sub-terms.
    </p><p>
        Compositionality aids understanding by ensuring that the semantics is modular
        and supports the use of simple <strong>equational reasoning</strong> techniques for proving properties of
        the semantics. When the set of semantic values is clear, a denotational semantics is often
        identified with the underlying valuation function.
    </p><p>
        Taking <tex>V</tex> the Haskell type <code>Integer</code> of integers and define a valuation function
        of type <code>Expr -&gt; Integer</code> (by following equations) we can define the denotational semantics of our expression language.
        <tex display="block">              \begin {align*}                  \llbracket \text {Val}   \space  n \rrbracket  &amp;= n  \\                   \llbracket \text {Add}   \space  e_1 \space  e_2 \rrbracket  &amp;=  \llbracket  e_1 \rrbracket  +  \llbracket  e_2 \rrbracket               \end {align*}         </tex>
        This definition satisfies the compositionality requirement obviously.
        Note that the symbol <tex>+</tex> has two different purposes.
        On the left side, it is a <strong>syntactic</strong> constructor for building terms,
        while on the right side, it is a <strong>semantic</strong> operator for adding integers. 
    </p><p>
        Compositionality simplifies reasoning because it allows us to 
        replace <strong>equals by equals</strong>. For example,
        <tex display="block">              \frac {                  \llbracket  e_1 \rrbracket  = n_1  \quad   \llbracket  e_2 \rrbracket  = n_2             }{                  \llbracket \text {Add}   \space  e_1 \space  e_2 \rrbracket  =                  \llbracket \text {Add}   \space  n_1 \space  n_2 \rrbracket              }         </tex>
        we can freely replace the two argument expressions of an addition by other expressions with the same meanings, 
        and the meaning of the whole addition will remain unchanged.
        Using the definition of the valuation function, we can prove this property.
        <tex display="block">              \begin {align*}                  \llbracket \text {Add}   \space  e_1 \space  e_2 \rrbracket  &amp;=                   \llbracket  e_1 \rrbracket  +  \llbracket  e_2 \rrbracket  ( \text {By definition of }  \llbracket- \rrbracket )  \\                  &amp;=  \llbracket  n_1 \rrbracket  +  \llbracket  n_2 \rrbracket  ( \text {Assumptions})  \\                   &amp;=  \llbracket \text {Add}   \space  n_1 \space  n_2 \rrbracket  ( \text {By definition of }  \llbracket- \rrbracket )              \end {align*}         </tex></p><p>
        Given that terms and their semantics are built up <strong>inductively</strong>,
        proofs about denotational semantics typically  proceed using <strong>structural induction</strong>.
        Let us show that our expression semantics is <strong>total</strong>,
        that is, for every expression <tex>e</tex> there is an integer <tex>n</tex> such that <tex>\llbracket  e \rrbracket  = n</tex>.
    </p>
 
   
   <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7414</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>   <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>     </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
        For the base case <tex>e =  \text {Val}   \space  n</tex>, we have <tex>\llbracket  e \rrbracket  = n</tex> trivially.
        For the inductive case <tex>e =  \text {Add}   \space  e_1 \space  e_2</tex>,
        we can assume by induction that <tex>\llbracket  e_1 \rrbracket  = n_1</tex> and <tex>\llbracket  e_2 \rrbracket  = n_2</tex>
        for some integers <tex>n_1</tex> and <tex>n_2</tex>. Then <tex>\llbracket  e \rrbracket  = n_1 + n_2</tex> by definition of the valuation function,
        indicates this case is also true. Therefore, the semantics is total.
    </mainmatter> </tree>
 
<p>
        The valuation function can be translated into a Haskell function
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">eval :: Expr -&gt; Integer
eval (Val n) = n
eval (Add x y) = eval x + eval y</code></pre>
<p>
        More generally, a denotational semantics can be viewed as an evaluator (or <strong>interpreter</strong>).
        Even <strong>eval</strong> is defined recursively, the semantics is compositional its behavior
        can be understood  as simply replacing the <strong>constructors</strong> for expressions by other functions.
        In this manner, a denotational semantics can also be viewed as an evaluation function that
        is defined by <strong>folding</strong> over the syntax of the source language.
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">eval :: Expr -&gt; Integer
eval = fold id (+)</code></pre>
<p>
        The fold operator captures the ideas of replacing constructors
        of the language by other functions
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">fold :: (Integer -&gt; a) -&gt; (a -&gt; a -&gt; a) -&gt; Expr -&gt; a 
fold f g (Val n) = f n
fold f g (Add x y) = g (fold f g x) (fold f g y)</code></pre>
<p>
        Note that the above semantics for expressions does not specify the order
        of evaluation. If we do wish to make evaluation order explicit 
        this requires the introduction of additional structure into the semantics,
        named <strong>abstract machines</strong> (Discuss later).
    </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7415</anchor>    <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>  <title><link href="cs-0006.xml" type="local" addr="cs-0006" title="Introduction to Programming Language Semantic">Introduction to Programming Language Semantic</link> › Small-Step Operational Semantics</title>  <parent>cs-0006</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
        Another popular approach to semantics is the <strong>operational approach</strong>,
        where the meaning of terms is defined using an <strong>execution relation</strong>
        that specifies how terms can be executed in an appropriate machine model.
        There are two basic forms of operational semantics:
        <ul><li><strong>small-step</strong>: describes the individual steps of execution
            </li>
            <li><strong>big-step</strong>: describes the overall results of execution
            </li></ul>
        In this section we consider the small-step approach, 
        which is also known as <strong>structural operational semantics</strong>.
    </p><p>
        Formally, a small-step operational semantics for a language <tex>T</tex> of syntactic terms
        comprises two components:
        a set <tex>S</tex> of <strong>execution states</strong> and 
        a <strong>transition relation</strong> of type <tex>S \to  S</tex> that specifies how terms can be executed.
        If there is a transition from state <tex>s</tex> to state <tex>s'</tex> in a single execution step, we write <tex>s \to  s'</tex>.
    </p><p>
        Arithmetic expressions have a simple small-step operational semantics,
        given by taking <tex>S</tex> as the Haskell type. And we define transition relation 
        on <code>Expr</code> by the following inference rules.
        <tex display="block">              \begin {align*}                  \frac {}{                      \text {Add} \space ( \text {Val} \space  n_1) \space ( \text {Val} \space  n_2) \to \text {Val} \space (n_1+n_2)                 }  \\                   \frac {x \to  x'}{ \text {Add}   \space  x \space  y \to \text {Add}   \space  x' \space  y}                   \quad                    \frac {y \to  y'}{ \text {Add}   \space  x \space  y \to \text {Add}   \space  x \space  y'}              \end {align*}         </tex></p><p>
        The first rule states that two values can be added to give a single value and is called a
        <strong>reduction</strong> (or <strong>contraction</strong>) rule.
        An expression that matches such a rule is termed a reducible expression or <strong>redex</strong>.
        The last two rules are called <strong>structural</strong> (or <strong>congruence</strong>) rules as 
        they specify how larger terms can be reduced.
    </p><p>
        The semantics is <strong>non-deterministic</strong> because an expression
        may have more than one possible transition.
        This is obviously from the structural rules, which allow either sub-expression to be reduced first.
    </p><p>
        We can now capture a the relation between the denotational and operational semantics,
        namely that making a transition does not change the denotation of an expression.
        <tex display="block">              \frac {                 e \to  e'             }{                  \llbracket e \rrbracket  =  \llbracket e' \rrbracket              }         </tex>
        This property can be proved by induction on the structure of the expression <tex>e</tex>.
        Note that by using the &quot;equals by equals&quot; and the assumption <tex>x \to  x'</tex> we can easily 
        prove the inductive case. The details are omitted here as it involves quite a bit of 
        case analysis. We will later see the <strong>principle of rule induction</strong>, which gives 
        a simpler and more direct way to prove such properties.
    </p><p>
        Evaluation of an expression using the small-step semantics proceeds by a series of zero
        or more transition steps. Formally we can write <tex>e \to ^* e'</tex> to indicate that <tex>e</tex> can be
        reduced to <tex>e'</tex> in zero or more steps.
        We can generate a transition tree that captures all possible execution
        paths for an expression. Using the list comprehension we can define a 
        function that returns the list of all expressions that can be reduced 
        from a given expression <tex>e</tex> in a single transition.
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">trans :: Expr -&gt; [Expr]
trans (Val n) = []
trans (Add (Val n) (Val m)) = [Val (n + m)]
trans (Add x y) = [Add x' y | x' &lt;- trans x] ++ [Add x y' | y' &lt;- trans y]</code></pre>
<p>
        We can define a Haskell datatype for transition trees 
        and an execution function that converts expressions into 
        transition trees.
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">data Tree a = Node a [Tree a]
exec :: Expr -&gt; Tree Expr
exec e = Node e [exec e' | e' &lt;- trans e]</code></pre>
<p>
        Though <code>exec</code> is defined recursively, its behavior can be understood as simply applying
        the identity function to give the root of the tree and the transition function to generate a 
        list of residual expressions to be processed to give the subtrees.
        A small-step semantics can be viewed as giving rise to an execution
        function that is defined by <strong>unfolding</strong> to transition trees.
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">exec :: Expr -&gt; Tree Expr
exec = unfold id trans</code></pre>
<p>
        The <code>unfold</code> function captures the idea of generating a tree 
        from a seed value <tex>x</tex> by applying a function <tex>f</tex> to give the root 
        and a function <tex>g</tex> to give a list of residual values to be processed
        for the subtrees.
    </p>
  <pre><code class="language-haskell">unfold :: (t -&gt; a) -&gt; (t -&gt; [t]) -&gt; t -&gt; Tree a
unfold f g x = Node (f x) [unfold f g x' | x' &lt;- g x]</code></pre>
<p>
        The operational semantics corresponds to <strong>unfolding to transition trees</strong>,
        while denotational semantics corresponds to <strong>folding over syntax trees</strong>.
        Thinking about semantics in terms of recursion operators reveals a duality
    </p><p>
        The above semantics for expressions does not specify the order of evaluation.
        But we can modify the inference rules to achieve this. Replace the second <tex>\text {Add}</tex> 
        rule by the following rule ensures the first argument of addition is 
        always reduced first.
        <tex display="block">              \frac {                 y \to  y'             }{                  \text {Add}  ( \text {Val} \space  n) \space  y  \to   \text {Add}  ( \text {Val} \space  n) \space  y'             }         </tex></p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7416</anchor>    <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>  <title><link href="cs-0006.xml" type="local" addr="cs-0006" title="Introduction to Programming Language Semantic">Introduction to Programming Language Semantic</link> › Rule induction</title>  <parent>cs-0006</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
        For denotational semantics we have structural induction,
        dual to this, for operational semantics we have <strong>rule induction</strong>.
        This allows us to perform proofs by considering the structure of the rules 
        that are used to define the semantics.
    </p><p>
        We introduce the idea of rule induction using a simple numeric example.
        We begin by inductively defining a set of natural numbers.
        <tex display="block">                  \frac {}{0 \in \mathbb {N} }  \quad                    \frac {n \in \mathbb {N} }{n+1 \in \mathbb {N} }         </tex>
        This is the standard definition of the natural numbers using peano axioms,
        where the first rule states that zero is a natural number and the second rule states that
        if <tex>n</tex> is a natural number then so is <tex>n+1</tex>.
    </p><p>
        For the inductively defined set <tex>\mathbb {N}</tex>. The principle of rule induction
        states that in order to prove a property <tex>P(n)</tex> for all natural numbers <tex>n</tex>,
        it suffices to prove that <tex>P(0)</tex> holds and that if <tex>P(n)</tex> holds then <tex>P(n+1)</tex> holds.
        <tex display="block">              \frac {                 P(0) \quad \forall  n \in \mathbb {N} . P(n) \to  P(n+1)             }{                  \forall  n \in \mathbb {N} . P(n)             }         </tex>
        Notice that this is the well-known <strong>principle of mathematical induction</strong>.
    </p><p>
        The concept of rule induction can easily be generalised to multiple base and 
        inductive cases, to rule with multiple preconditions and so on.
        For the small-step semantics of expressions, we have one base case and two inductive cases.
        Hence if we want to show that some property <tex>P(e,e')</tex> on pairs of expression holds for 
        all transition <tex>e \to  e'</tex>, we can use rule induction:
        <tex display="block">              \frac {                  \begin {align*}                     P( \text {Add} \space ( \text {Val} \space  n_1) \space ( \text {Val} \space  n_2), \text {Val} \space (n_1+n_2))  \\                       \forall  x \to  x'. P(x,x') \to  P( \text {Add} \space  x \space  y, \text {Add} \space  x' \space  y)  \\                       \forall  y \to  y'. P(y,y') \to  P( \text {Add} \space  x \space  y, \text {Add} \space  x \space  y')                  \end {align*}             }{                  \forall  e \to  e'. P(e,e')             }         </tex>
        We write <tex>\forall  x \to  y.P(x,y)</tex> as shorthand for 
        <tex display="block">\forall  x,y.x \to  y \Rightarrow  P(x,y)</tex>. Now we give the proof 
        of the property <tex>\llbracket e \rrbracket  =  \llbracket e' \rrbracket</tex> for all transitions <tex>e \to  e'</tex>.
        <tex display="block">              \forall  e \to  e'.  \llbracket e \rrbracket  =  \llbracket e' \rrbracket          </tex></p>
 
   
   <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>7417</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>   <date><year>2024</year> <month>3</month> <day>11</day></date>     </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
        The proof consists of three parts: the base case, the reduction rule and the structural rule.
        <tex display="block">              \begin {align*}                  \llbracket \text {Add} \space ( \text {Val} \space  n) \space ( \text {Val} \space  m) \rrbracket                  &amp;=  \llbracket \text {Val} \space  n \rrbracket  +  \llbracket \text {Val} \space  m \rrbracket   \\                  &amp;= n + m  \\                  &amp;=  \llbracket \text {Val} \space (n+m) \rrbracket               \end {align*}         </tex>
        and
        <tex display="block">              \begin {align*}                  \llbracket \text {Add} \space  x \space  y \rrbracket                  &amp;=  \llbracket x \rrbracket  +  \llbracket y \rrbracket    \\                  &amp;=  \llbracket x' \rrbracket  +  \llbracket y \rrbracket  ( \text {By assumption } \llbracket x \rrbracket = \llbracket x' \rrbracket )  \\                  &amp;=  \llbracket \text {Add} \space  x' \space  y \rrbracket               \end {align*}         </tex>
        and 
        <tex display="block">              \begin {align*}                  \llbracket \text {Add} \space  x \space  y \rrbracket                  &amp;=  \llbracket x \rrbracket  +  \llbracket y \rrbracket    \\                  &amp;=  \llbracket x \rrbracket  +  \llbracket y' \rrbracket  ( \text {By assumption } \llbracket y \rrbracket = \llbracket y' \rrbracket )  \\                   &amp;=  \llbracket \text {Add} \space  x \space  y' \rrbracket               \end {align*}         </tex>
    </mainmatter> </tree>
 
</mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>